Hi, welcome back to Arya Nagarjuna.
We're still in the middle of Chapter 10,
which is "An Examination
of Fire and Firewood".
And this was supposed to clear it up,
rather the seer is there before the seeing
and especially before the thing you see,
or is the seer come later, or
do they come at the same time?
Is it even possible that
we are seeing things
the way we think we are?
If you are not seeing things
the way you think you're seeing things,
then sooner or later you get in trouble,
you start fighting with your
husband, or you do things
that don't make sense
to make things happen.
Like, I don't know, in your
business, you take actions
which don't result in the
result you think they do
because you don't understand this question
of is the seer seeing something
before the thing is there,
or is the thing there first,
and then the person sees it later?
Of course, it applies to Medicine Buddha.
If you're doing a mantra,
what's the time frame
between you and the mantra?
Do you come first and
then you do the mantra?
But how can you come first if
you're a mantra practitioner
because you haven't done a mantra yet?
So actually, the mantra should come first,
and then the person who
says it should come later,
but then a mantra can't say
itself, and it gets confusing.
If it gets confusing to you,
you are on the right track.
If it's not confusing,
you're on the wrong track.
If it seems confusing to you,
then it's shaking up your
normal way of seeing things,
which according to
Buddhism is always wrong.
You have always been wrong.
Your opinion about whether
the mantra came first
or the mantra sayer came
first, or how the mantra works.
If you think you know, you're
probably making a mistake.
And then when you say the
mantras, they're not as effective.
It's not as powerful.
It's much more powerful
if you understand how it really works.
And it's like the relationship
between wood and fire, firewood and fire.
So we're halfway through our examination
of firewood and fire. Here we go.
We're going to go to verse
number eight, and it says,
,GAL TE SHING LTOS ME YIN LA,
,GAL TE ME LTOS SHING YIN NA,
,GANG LTOS ME DANG SHING 'GYUR BA,
,DANG POR GRUB PA GANG ZHIG YIN,
This is a question from Arya Nagarjuna.
GAL TE SHING LTOS ME YIN LA
Is it the case that we have a fire
which is depending on the firewood?
Or GAL TE ME LTOS SHING YIN NA
is it a case that we have wood
which depends on its identity,
firewood, which depends
on its identity for fire?
So the fire would have to come first
because it can't be
firewood if it came first
before the fire.
You have to have a fire.
Then you say, oh, this wood is firewood.
But if you don't have the wood first,
before it's firewood,
how can you have a fire?
And how can you have a fire
from wood which is not firewood?
Something's fishy.
Something's wrong.
GANG LTOS ME DANG SHING 'GYUR BA
And somebody says,
"I think they kind of
depend on each other."
The fire needs the wood to start burning,
but the wood needs the fire
before you can call it firewood.
So somebody says, "Geshe-la, I think
it's kind of like they're
depending on each other."
DANG POR GRUB PA GANG ZHIG YIN
But then we have to still have a question
of which came first,
the chicken or the egg?
Which came first, the
firewood or the fire?
DANG POR GRUB PA GANG ZHIG YIN
means which one came first?
Why? Why is that important?
Now, listen and think about it.
Because the second thing to come
always depends on the first thing to come.
The second thing that comes always depends
on the first thing that comes.
Curing cancer with a mantra come second,
and that depends on the
mantra coming first, right?
But if it's that the mantra
depends on the curing,
in other words, if it doesn't cure cancer,
then it's not really magical words, is it?
It's not really a mantra.
So in that case, first
you should cure somebody
with some kind of words
and then those words
would become a mantra.
But then how do you know what words to say
if you don't know if they're a mantra yet?
You could just read the side
of a cereal box or something,
and see if it helps.
So it doesn't get to be a
mantra until you cure somebody,
but then if it doesn't get to be a mantra
until you cure somebody,
you'd have to keep saying different words
until something worked, and
then that would be a mantra.
You see what I mean?
So don't forget that
the second thing to come
has to depend on the first thing to come.
Is it that the cancer is
cured rests on the mantra,
or is it that it's the
mantra rests on the cure
because the mantra is not special words
until there's something happens from it.
GAL TE SHING LTOS ME YIN NA
If it's the fire that came first,
and then that depends on the wood,
ME GRUB PA LA SGRUB PAR 'GYUR
Then fire could've happened with no wood.
If the fire comes first,
and then the wood becomes firewood,
well, then the fire
doesn't depend on the wood
because the thing it depends
on has to come first, right?
If the fire comes first and
then it depends on the wood,
then in the very beginning of the fire
there could be fire with no wood,
before it was depending on the wood.
BUD PAR BYA BA'I SHING LA YANG
If the wood came first... by
the way, we're on Verse 9,
ME MED PAR NI 'GYUR PA YIN
then without a fire the
wood would be firewood.
Before there was any fire,
the wood would be firewood.
Before you saw a fire come from it,
you could call it firewood.
All right, and we have a
picture here of firewood.
And a...
the idea is, I mean,
it's not firewood yet
until there's a fire.
It looks like somebody tied it up.
It looks like somebody
cut it in a certain way.
We don't know for sure yet
though that it's firewood.
We don't know if someone's
not using these sticks
for something else.
So until there's a fire,
this is not firewood,
and until there's
firewood, there's no fire.
So maybe things don't
happen the way we thought.
Maybe the mantra doesn't fix the cancer.
Maybe something else is creating
the mantra and the cancer,
and the fix of the cancer.
Like maybe our seeds,
maybe our mental seeds.
Then, well, how do you use that, Geshe-la?
How do you apply that to your life?
Well, then it makes sense
to save animals' lives
because then the mantra would work against
the cancer, for example.
There would be seeds in your mind
for a cause and effect
relationship between the mantra
and the curing the cancer.
I did a three-year retreat,
2000 to 2003.
And I remember we had
a lady in the retreat.
She wasn't from our lineage.
She was from a different
lineage but she begged me,
"Could I set up a cabin?
Could I do this 3-year retreat?"
We had, I don't know, five, six people
in different cabins, yurts. And she said,
"Can I do it with you guys?"
And we said okay.
And she got permission from her teacher.
And then I remember...
before the retreat and after the retreat,
we couldn't talk during the retreat, but
we used to have very intense discussions,
and it was a very interesting question.
She would say, "The power of your teacher
does not come from you."
Everything else maybe comes from you.
Everything else comes from your seeds,
but the power of your teacher
is just in your teacher,
and that doesn't come from you.
Whether you're a good
person or a bad person,
it doesn't matter.
What seeds you have doesn't matter.
If a person is your
teacher, then there's power.
The person has power.
Then we'd say, "Well,
yeah, but Buddha said it."
The first lines of this book,
Buddha said, "Everything comes from causes
and everything comes from seeds."
That's the first lines of
Nagarjuna's most famous book.
GANG GIS RTEN CING 'BREL BAR 'BYUNG
'GAG PA MED PA SKYE MED PA
Those are the first words:
everything comes from seeds.
So it's not that a mantra has power.
It's not that a mantra has power
even if it has been spoken by a Buddha.
If you don't have the
seeds for it to have power,
it doesn't have power.
Or else the Buddha was wrong.
Or else the person you say has the power
didn't have the power.
Okay, got it?
If the Buddha has power in
and of himself or herself,
then everything they say is true.
If the Buddha said all
things come from seeds
and even the power of the
Buddha comes from seeds.
Okay, got it?
And it can't be wrong because
the Buddha that you say
doesn't come from seeds, said it.
Got it?
All right.
All right, here we go.
That's very Nagarjuna, right?
All right.
Next verse.
,GAL TE DNGOS PO GANG LTOS 'GRUB,
,DE NYID LA YANG LTOS NAS NI,
,LTOS BYA GANG YIN DE 'GRUB NA,
,GANG LA LTOS NAS GANG ZHIG 'GRUB,
If the fire depends on the firewood,
then the fire...
If the wood came first
and the fire came second,
then LTOS BYA GANG YIN DE 'GRUB NA
if the thing being
depended upon by the fire
which is the firewood,
GANG LA LTOS NAS GANG ZHIG 'GRUB
what did the firewood depend
on to be called firewood?
So, okay, I understand the
dependence goes one way.
If I say is there a dependent origination?
Is there a dependent
relationship with fire?
Then you say yeah.
- Well, what?
- Well, the fire depends on the firewood.
You can't have a fire without some fuel.
- Yeah, but on the other hand,
the wood depends on the fire.
That's what it says here.
LTOS BYA means the wood that
the fire is depending upon.
GANG YIN DE 'GRUB NA
As soon as you have the firewood,
GANG LA LTOS NAS GANG ZHIG 'GRUB
well what did it depend
on to be called firewood?
That's a question.
I like to call it a ladder with no wall.
Here's a picture of it.
It took me a while.
I was trying to make
a ladder with no wall.
It's almost impossible,
but
anyway, it didn't come out that great.
But try to imagine a ladder
that's leaning on nothing.
Then that's what it would
be if the fire was firewood
before the fire starting,
then you could have a ladder.
You could get up on a ladder
that wasn't leaning on a wall.
That leaning on a wall is dependence,
and that's dependent origination.
And we're going to talk a lot
about the words for dependence
and what dependence means.
Does the curing cancer
depend on the mantra
or does the mantra depend
on curing the cancer?
Or do they both depend on something else?
That's what we would say.
And that's what Nagarjuna would say.
There's a reason why we
took our bodhichitta vows
from whose ceremony?
[Student] Nagarjuna.
[GMR] Nagarjuna, okay.
We took our vows, which
is the permission we need
to study Medicine Buddha.
We have to take vows and
the most famous ceremony
is Nagarjuna.
So maybe Nagarjuna knows
something about Medicine Buddha.
Okay, all right.
Here we go. Verse 11.
,DNGOS PO LTOS GRUB GANG YIN PA,
,DE MA GRUB NA JI LTAR LTOS,
,CI STE GRUB PA LTOS SHE NA,
,DE NI LTOS PAR MI RUNG NGO,
DNGOS PO LTOS GRUB GANG YIN PA
There's a very important
word here called LTOS GRUB,
and this is interesting for us.
It means things happen
because of other things.
And the most famous, I
think, Sugeng's text,
the Mixed Nuts' text.
We are translating a very
difficult commentary by Vasubandhu
on the Wheel of Life.
And you will see there
the definition of dependent origination.
The definition of dependence,
pratītya samutpāda (pratitya samutpada),
is LTOS GRUB.
LTOS GRUB, here's the word LTOS GRUB.
LTOS GRUB means
everything that changes happens
based on something else.
Everything that changes
in the universe happens
depending on something else.
'DI 'BYUNG BAS NA DE 'BYUNG
And the very, very
earliest statement of it
is by Lord Buddha, and he said,
"If this happens, that will happen.
And if that happens, this must happen."
And he's like this, you can see him.
"If this happens, then this will happen."
It's like your mom used to tell you,
"If you do this, this is going to happen,
and if this happens, is
because you did this."
Then I don't know, after
that it got complicated.
People started calling
it dependent origination.
In the beginning, it was very simple.
If you do this, guys,
you're going to get this.
That's LTOS GRUB.
DNGOS PO LTOS GRUB GANG YIN PA
DE MA GRUB NA JI LTAR LTOS
How could fire depend on wood?
And now we get into a
tricky thing with Nagarjuna.
And it seems a little
unfair.
If you back him into a corner,
if you say, "Yeah, but
you can't have a fire
without a firewood."
And he's, "Okay, okay,
but the fire you think you
can't get without firewood,
it doesn't exist anyway."
And you're like, "Wait, wait.
Now, you're changing things."
And he says,
"Yeah, well, don't tell me
the fire depends on the wood
because the fire can't exist anyway."
- Well, what do you mean?
- The fire you're thinking of can't exist.
- Why?
- Because you think it comes from wood.
- But I'm trying to
prove it comes from wood.
- I know, but that means you
think it comes from wood.
- Yeah, I think it comes from wood,
that's what I'm trying to prove to you.
- But the fire you think comes from wood,
can't come from wood,
so you can't prove the
fire comes from wood
because the fire you want
to prove comes from wood
doesn't exist.
And it's like you're
frustrated, you're like,
"Man, I was trying to
prove something to you."
It's like having a
discussion with your wife.
DNGOS PO LTOS GRUB GANG YIN PA,
DE MA GRUB NA JI LTAR LTOS
CI STE GRUB PA LTOS SHE NA
Then the other guy, it's funny.
CI STE means well, what the hell!
The guy said, "I don't care."
CI STE is a very short word, right?
CI STE
But it means ah, anyway.
The guy's got CI STE, CI STE.
Anyway, the fire doesn't
depend on the wood.
DE NI LTOS PAR MI RUNG NGO
And then Nagarjuna says,
"No, you can't have a ladder
leaning on a wall that's not there."
You can't have a ladder
leaning or depending on a wall
if the wall's not there.
- What's not there?
- There's no firewood there.
- Why?
- There's no fire yet,
how can it be firewood?
Maybe it's, I don't know,
wood they're going to use
to build a cafe when they
get a permit in three years.
Something like that.
You don't know what the wood is yet.
All right.
And then I like this picture,
and this is an old picture
that we use in DCI.
It's a pen, parts of a pen on a table.
I hope so.
The point here is that the
resting of the pen on the desk
is also not self existing.
We went through many
times why it's not a pen
until the seed opens in your mind.
We talked about that countless times.
But now if you look at the
pen resting on the table,
the pen resting on the desk,
that's also coming from your seeds.
The dependence of the pen on
the parts sitting on the desk
is also coming from your seed.
Okay, all right, next verse.
Now some guy says,
"I have an option."
- What?
- The fire depends on the wood
and it doesn't depend on
the wood at the same time.
How's that?
He's getting frustrated and saying
the fire doesn't depend on the wood
because it's not a firewood yet,
and the firewood needs
the fire before it can...
He says, "Look, Ok, Nagarjuna,
I have a suggestion.
Let's do both at the same time."
The fire depends on the wood
and it doesn't depend on
the wood at the same time.
How's that?
Then you're happy and I'm happy."
,SHING LA LTOS PA'I ME MED DE,
,SHING LA MA LTOS ME YANG MED,
There's no fire that could depend on wood,
and there's no fire that
couldn't depend on the wood.
Therefore, ME LA LTOS PA'I SHING MED DE
There's no wood that
could depend on the fire,
and there's no wood that
couldn't depend on the fire.
There's no fire that
doesn't depend on wood,
but there's no fire that
does depend on wood.
There's no wood that depends
on the fire to be firewood,
and there's no wood that
doesn't depend on the fire
to be firewood.
How's that? Let's leave it like that.
The other guys said,
"You can have your cake
and eat it too."
And Nagarjuna's answer is, ridiculous.
And I try to make a ridiculous picture.
Pachi, are you ready? I don't know.
I hope it's ridiculous.
It's a cup on a table.
I don't know.
I tried really hard on this one.
The cup is on the table
but it's not on the table
because the table is on
the cup at the same time.
The cup is on the table and
the table is on the cup.
So Nagarjuna, you don't
have to struggle deciding
whether the fire rests on the wood
or the wood rests on the fire.
How about both?
Let's do both.
Unfortunately, the cup
would only be one, right?
And then it'd be difficult
to make a photo of it.
Almost impossible, I think so.
All right, let's go to the next verse.
He splits the next verse into two.
And when he does that,
there's always an
important reason for that.
So we're going to take
half a verse which is 13a.
And it's very simple.
,ME NI GZHAN LAS MI 'ONG STE,
,SHING LA'ANG ME NI YOD MA YIN,
And what this means is the other guy says,
"You can see it. If you can see it,
If you can see fire burns wood,
then fire does have a
nature, and it burns things."
Don't tell me nothing has its own nature.
You don't have to be a philosopher
to see that things are not empty.
They are something, they're not empty.
Fire is not empty. - Why?
- You can see it burns wood.
If a fire burns something,
then you can't say it has
no nature. It has a nature.
What's its nature?
It burns things, duh, you can see.
Stop hassling me, that's all.
The other guy's like, "Open
your eyes, Nagarjuna, look."
And probably he'd lit
a match or something.
He said, "Look, the fire is
burning the wood. Okay, got it?"
Don't tell me it doesn't
have a nature of its own.
Don't say the match fire is empty
because it's not empty
because it's doing something.
If you can see that it's doing something,
it's not empty.
Don't give me this empty stuff.
So that's a very, very...
In Tibetan it's
MES BUD SHING SREG PA MNGON SUM GYIS
MTHONG BAS NGO BOS YOD DO ZHE NA
The other guy says, Look, if
a fire burns a piece of wood,
then MNGON SUM GYIS MTHONG BAS
if you can see it with your own eyeballs,
then the fire has its own nature,
and it's not empty of
any nature of its own.
Now, we're going to get
to Nagarjuna's answer.
But first of all,
he says,
and there's an American
English expression:
Seeing is believing. Seeing is believing."
The other guy says, "Look,
seeing is believing."
And Nagarjuna says, "Let
me show you a picture now."
Let me show you a picture with somebody
with certain glasses on.
And there's an expression
in American English called
"looking at things with
the rose colored glasses."
Actually I gave a talk once long ago
and I bought 100 pairs of these glasses.
I handed them out to everybody,
and I said, "Is the world pink?"
And they're all like, "Yes."
And I, "Yeah, I can see it's pink."
So it must be. You said
if you can see something
is a certain way, it must be that way.
A guy says, "Yeah, okay.
Well, put on these glasses.
Is everything pink?"
- Yeah.
- Is it really that way?
- No.
- Yes, it is, because you're seeing it.
Seeing is believing.
If you see everything
in the universe is pink,
then it must be pink.
That was your argument.
Then the guy says, "No, no,
you've you messed up my eyes.
You put these pink sunglasses on me."
- Yeah, well, maybe
without the sunglasses,
your eyes are messed up.
All right?
Maybe you're messing up
everything all the time anyway.
And that's the idea.
Okay, so the Wheel of Life teaching
is basically that your
equipment is messed up.
Your eyes are already
tinted. And you can say,
"Fire must depend on wood
because any fool can see it."
- Yeah, but if the way you look at things,
you're always a fool. All right?
Okay, here we go to the
next half verse again.
,DE BZHIN SHING GI LHAG MA NI,
,SONG DANG MA SONG BGOM PAS BSTAN,
Now, Nagarjuna, he goes
an interesting strategy,
and by the way, in this whole book
and most of Nagarjuna's books
are like a military campaign.
I saw a movie about Alexander
the Great. He's so cool.
I mean, he was a brutal killer
but his first great battle,
I think he's got 40,000 Macedonians
against a million Persians. And he's 21.
And it's 20-1, and he goes out there,
and he's like, "Okay, I got an idea."
And his strategy is so cool.
He rides out with 100 guys,
and they take off that
way so that the soldiers
are facing the soldiers, right?
He comes out with like 100 guys,
and he runs that way with his horses.
And the other general's
like, "Where's he gone?"
- I don't know.
- We're supposed to go like
this and fight with each other.
- What's he doing?
- He's gone somewhere.
- But you, you, you, you, follow him.
Find out where he's going.
And then he circled around.
The general was no longer
protected, the Persian general,
and he...
[shooting sound]
Okay, got it?
Now, why are we talking about that?
Nagarjuna does the same thing.
He sees this whole thing
almost like a military campaign.
And here's his next move.
Here's his next move.
DE BZHIN SHING GI LHAG MA NI
LHAG MA means leftover, right, Tim?
LHAG MA means leftover.
He says, "Look, let's just stop there
about the fire and the firewood."
It's been going on too long.
It's already two classes.
Let's just finish it.
He says, "Anything else you wanted to say
about the firewood, just stop."
And the guy said "Whoa, wait."
He says, "Go back to
SONG DANG MA SONG BGOM.
Go back to the chapter
about walking down a path,
which is the second chapter.
"Going and Coming"
He says, "Look,
I don't have to do this
whole argument with you."
I'm tired of this chapter.
we got to go on to the next chapter.
It's already too much time.
Let's get onto the next chapter.
If you want to talk more about
anything else about firewood,
can you just go back and
read the second chapter.
Again, I told you everything.
What did he tell us in the second chapter?
Anybody?
Remember something about
there's three parts to the path.
Three parts to a road.
Do you remember?
There's the part you already walked on,
then there's the part
you're going to walk on,
and then there's the part
you're walking on now.
Now, how wide is the part
you're walking on now
is the question.
Okay, like your foot goes like,
here's the path and your
foot heels touches first,
and then your toes take off, right?
Heel, foot, toe.
This part is the path you already went on.
This part is the path you didn't go on.
Now, exactly where's the
line between those two?
- Well, it must be halfway.
- Well, let's wait until
you put your foot down.
- Okay, and you want to
call it halfway the foot?
- Yeah, yeah, okay.
- Well, where's the
halfway point on your foot?
You can't find it.
You can't really find it.
Any line you draw, if
you can see the line,
it already has width.
So it already has a part
that you went on already and a part
that you didn't go on already.
- Okay, we'll split that one, Geshe-la.
- Okay, let's split that one.
And then that has a
width, and that has a part
that you went on and a
part that you didn't go on.
And the answer is there's no part
that you're walking on now.
You always either walked on something
or going to walk on something,
but you're never walking on something.
So if you're not walking on something,
how can you ever have
walked somewhere before
and how can you ever go
into walk on something?
Because you're not walking.
- Geshe-la, it's all bullshit.
You're just splitting hairs.
- Yeah, but no, it's important.
You think you're walking but you're not.
Maybe the path is moving.
Okay?
Maybe your mental pictures
are getting bigger,
bigger, bigger, bigger,
as you go through a door,
bigger, bigger, bigger door,
smaller, smaller, smaller door.
You call it walking to a door.
But maybe you're not walking to a door.
Maybe your mind is making
small door, big door, big door,
big door, big door,
little, little door, little door,
little, little, little door.
Maybe you're standing in
the same place all the time.
Something like that.
Geshe-la, what's the point of all that?
Well, then it means
you're creating the door,
and you're creating the
passage to the door,
and that means you can
go anywhere you want.
If it's coming from here,
then you could walk planets.
You could act out your bodhichitta.
That's how you're going to be a Buddha.
- Oh, if you say Medicine Buddha mantra,
you become Medicine Buddha.
- Yeah, what's that all about?
- Well, then you can
go to different planets
and help people at the same time.
- Why?
Because the planet gets
bigger, bigger, bigger
when you arrive and the planet
gets smaller, smaller, smaller
when you go to the next planet.
That's all coming from your mind.
Hey, why not just do it
all at the same time?
And then you're everywhere.
And you can help everybody
at the same time.
That's all.
If the travel to other planets
was coming from anywhere
else except your seeds,
it's impossible.
You can't. - Why?
- There's no place you are now.
Okay, got it?
It's very sexy.
Because of emptiness you
can become Medicine Buddha.
And if you don't understand that,
you will never become
Medicine Buddha. Got it?
So he says, "Go back to
what I told you before."
Now, Grandpa likes to
take you back to the...
I could just go onto the next verse,
but why don't I take you
back to the last verse.
And we don't have it on the thing.
Anyway, I went back and got
the whole second chapter.
It's all about that walking thing.
Nagarjuna, you can feel
like he's almost impatient.
Now he wants to get onto
his eleventh chapter, right?
He says, "Just remember what I told you
about the walking thing."
By the way, every text I
saw or many of the texts,
they misspelled the walking thing.
And if you spell it wrong,
it becomes meditation.
And then it gets messy.
So it's useful to have the Sanskrit.
All right.
Which means, I don't
know, I was in a mood,
the next picture we're going to look at.
To me, the most important
application of fire
is making a pizza in a firebrick oven.
Do we have any around here? I don't know.
Yeah?
So if you can't decide,
is the fire burning the pizza
or is the pizza causing the
fire to be called the fire
because it gets cooked by the thing?
I think
the discussion of whether
the pizza defines the fire
or the fire cooks the pizza
what's it similar to?
What did Nagarjuna just say?
What did he just say?
You can't find.
[TL] You can't find the now.
[GMR] Yeah, you can't find the now,
therefore you cannot bake a pizza.
And that's why they're parallel.
That's why he wants to
bring the second chapter
into the tenth chapter.
You can't find a place
where the pizza is cooking.
In time, temporarily,
you cannot find a place
where the pizza is done.
It doesn't exist.
He's just sitting in front
of the guy and he's like
I'm so tired of this fire.
Agni - Indana
The guy says, "Any last
words you want to give me?"
- You can't have a pizza.
- Why?
- There's no moment when it's done.
Got it?
Because the pizza doesn't depend on fire,
and the fire is not a pizza
fire until the pizza is done.
Got it?
I don't know why I decided to use a pizza.
Hey, Jigme, let's buy a pizza.
Okay.
I'll just tell you the
English of the old verse.
That part I've already translated.
"First of all, having gone is not going,
neither is not having gone going,
and yet, except for having
gone and not having gone,
you can never be stepping."
That's part of the lines
that he's talking about.
All right.
Oh, and then there's another
verse later on that's relevant,
and he says, "Fire as an
example to establish seeing
is not something which can
having gone or not gone,
or stepping down, offers
a reply to the one
who is tied to seeing."
In other words, if you
always believe your eyes,
then I'll give you the
argument about walking.
You cannot always believe your eyes.
- Why?
- I told you about the walking thing.
It looks like there's a
place where you're walking,
but there's not.
So don't trust your eyes.
That's the subject we're on right now.
Don't tell me the fire
must depend on the wood
because you can see it burns
when there's wood there.
Then we say, don't trust your eyes.
You also think you're walking, don't you?
You also think you're walking
to a door, but you never are.
- But my eyes tell me so.
- Yeah, that's the problem.
[laughing]
All right.
We can go to verse 14.
This is a long run, I'm sorry.
I think Nagarjuna also wants
to get onto the next verse.
Nagarjuna here, he's
kind of making a review,
and he says, "Let's look at
the four possibilities here."
,SHING NYID ME NI MA YIN TE,
,SHING LAS GZHAN LA ME YANG MED,
,ME NI SHING DANG LDAN MA YIN,
,ME LA SHING MED DER DE MED,
Here's the four possibilities.
So Nagarjuna is kind of summarizing.
- Look, wood is not fire.
Wood is not the fire.
- Why?
And by the way, I want
you to think about this
because the way Choney Lama does it
is a little bit tricky.
You're ready?
Wood is not the fire
because in that case, the
agent would be the action.
That makes wood the agent.
So it's not that fire's burning wood,
it's that wood is feeding a fire.
Okay?
Who came first, the chicken or the egg?
Is the fire burning the wood?
Is that what this chapter is all about?
And Choney Lama says, "Oh no, no.
The wood is feeding the fire."
The fire is the object of the action,
not the agent.
The wood is feeding the fire.
Then the guy says,
"Well, I thought the fire
was burning the wood.
I thought the fire was the agent
and the wood was the object."
Then Nagarjuna says,
"Well, think about it.
You also thought you were walking."
I'll say it again.
By the way, I'm sorry,
we have to go so fast.
We're trying to get through
this book in five years,
and this is the only way.
Right now, today, we
are moving at one wisdom
per five years.
If we move slower, it's
going to be 20 years.
Really.
Okay, here we go.
You're meant to look at these videos again
and again, and again until you get it.
All right.
Wood is not the fire because then
the agent would be the action.
When you say it that way, who's the agent?
I'll say it again.
Wood is not the fire because
if the wood was the fire,
the agent would be the action.
He's saying the fire is
the object of the wood.
The wood is feeding the fire.
That kind of implies the wood came first
and then it's feeding the fire.
And he says,
"I don't want you to say the
fire is burning the wood."
Then the fire came first and
the wood came second, right?
Sorry, yeah, the fire came
first and the wood came second.
All right.
So are they the same thing?
Is the fire the wood? - No.
I mean, either the fire
is burning the wood
or the wood is feeding the fire.
But they can't really be
happening at the same time.
Then the second one is, is the
wood separate from the fire?
And he says, "No, it's not."
- Why?
- Because when you say
separate from the fire,
you think they never overlap.
When you say Rebecca is
separate from Michael,
then what you mean is they're
not Siamese twins somewhere.
She's over there. I'm over here.
So there must be some line between them.
That means they don't overlap.
They can't overlap.
- Well, okay, if they never overlap,
then they can't have a relationship.
Not possible.
If the fire never touches the wood,
there can't be burning.
But if it does touch the wood,
then there's a place where
the wood is the fire.
- No, no, no, the wood is over there,
the fire is over there,
Geshe-la. And they touch.
- Yeah, but where do they touch?
- There's a spot where
they touch each other,
so they have to overlap
in a tiny space there.
If they don't, then there's
always a line between them.
Then no one can burn the other
because it never touches the other.
If it does touch the other,
then there must be some
kind of overlap there.
If the wood is not separate from the fire,
you couldn't have the
fire burning the wood
because the fire is the wood.
All right. Does the fire involve the wood?
- No.
- Is the fire completely devoid of wood?
- No, because then it wouldn't burn.
So these are the four choices.
I'll say them again.
And again, you don't have to
understand it the first time,
just keep listening to it.
If you think you understood Nagarjuna
the first time you read it,
you must be drunk or something.
All right.
Wood is not the fire
because then the agent of the
action would be the action.
Wood is not separate from the fire
because if they were separate,
then there couldn't be a fire.
Fire doesn't involve
wood because if it did,
some part of the fire would be the wood.
And if you say that's
ridiculous, then I say,
well, okay, then water can cause fire.
- Why?
- Because they don't touch.
If fire were devoid of wood,
there would be no fire.
If fire had no relationship to wood,
how could you have a fire?
What's really happening
when fire burns wood?
You have the karma to
have a fire. That's all.
You have the seeds to have a fire.
The wood is not causing the fire.
The wood is not feeding the fire,
and the fire's not burning the wood.
Your seeds are opening.
That's all. That's all.
That's what Nagarjuna wants you to...
That's all he wants you to understand.
The fire is not burning the wood
and the wood is not feeding the fire.
Your seeds are opening and you see a fire.
Stop thinking that the
wood causes the fire
or stop thinking that the
fire is burning the wood.
Stop thinking like that.
My seeds are opening into wood.
My seeds are opening into fire.
That's all.
Start trying to think like that.
My seeds are opening into
Medicine Buddha mantra.
And then my seeds are opening
into the cancer is stopping.
My seeds put them together.
My seeds make them cause and effect.
They are not cause and effect.
They can't be cause and effect
because one can't touch the other.
No more than
where you went and where you're
going to go can never touch.
[laughing]
Okay.
All right.
Let's go to the next verse.
I'm sorry, this one's really long.
,MA DANG SHING GIS BDAG DANG NI,
,NYE BAR LEN PA'I RIM PA KUN,
,BUM RNAM SOGS DANG LHAN CIG TU,
,MA LUS PAR NI RNAM PAR BSHAD
This is a pretty profound verse.
He says, look, we spent all
these two classes talking
about wood and fire.
NYE BAR LEN PA'I RIM PA
I want you to apply that to
all actions by all people.
For example, to what we had
in the previous chapters:
seeing, hearing, smelling,
tasting, feeling.
There's an agent which is your eyeball.
There's a blue color out there.
The agent acts towards the object.
Try: when you're struggling
with understanding
how you can see something,
when you're struggling with
understanding how mantra works,
please just go back to
the fire and the wood.
That's what he's saying.
He says, "Use it for everything."
Then he says BUM RNAM. BUM PA, Tim knows.
Coffee cup.
And SNAM BU means a bolt of cloth.
He's just taking two things in the room.
The eyeglasses and the coffee.
What I said about the
fire and the firewood,
what I said about the eye,
eyeball and the blue color -
Look, he's saying it's
the same with everything.
Eyeglasses, coffee cups,
vases, bolts of cloth.
It's the same with everything.
MA LUS PAR NI RNAM PAR BSHAD
You can explain every god
damn thing in the world
if you just get this fire
and firewood thing straight.
What?
The fire is not burning the firewood
and the firewood is not feeding the fire.
If you can get it, okay! then
you understand everything.
Apply it to everything.
I have a picture here.
I was trying to think of
two things in the world.
Two things in the world.
I don't know, they should
be a refrigerator and a car.
Maybe I messed it up.
Oh, there you go.
Yeah, you can apply it to
everything: refrigerators, cars,
bolts of cloth.
In the old days, they didn't
have cars and refrigerators,
so he had to say bolts of cloth and water.
Water vase is a popular example
because there was no plumbing
in any of the houses.
You had to have a vase.
So it's a good example
because it's always there.
You always have one.
If you've ever lived
in a village in India,
the 'kailash',
the water vase or pot is
a very important thing in your life.
That's all your water for the day.
You walk a mile to the well,
you get it, and you put it on your head.
You bring it home and
that's what you wash from,
that's what you cook from.
That's what you... Yeah.
Okay, I always got another verse here,
I don't know what happened.
,GANG DAG BDAG DANG DNGOS PO RNAMS,
,DE BCAS NYID DANG THA DAD PAR,
,RTOG PA DE DAG
Oh, this is the final verse,
I think, and it's very funny.
Yeah, it's the final verse.
Very cute.
He says, look:
,GANG DAG BDAG DANG DNGOS PO RNAMS,
,DE BCAS NYID DANG THA DAD PAR,
If you think the fire and
the wood are the same thing,
or if you think the fire
and the wood are separate,
MKHAS SO SNYAM DU MI SEMS SO
I don't think you're so smart.
[laughing]
MKHAS SO means...
MKHAS PA, right Tim?
Sage, yeah.
If thou thinkest that
the fire is the wood,
or if thou thinkest that the
fire and the wood are separate,
I don't thinketh that thou is too smart.
And that's his last word
and he's kind of insulting.
Last word.
MKHAS SO SNYAM means
if you think you're a smart guy,
MI SEMS, I don't think so.
If you don't get the fire-firewood thing,
then you're a fool.
That's all. All right.
And if you're a fool,
then you're always going to be suffering.
Somehow, you're always
going to be suffering.
Now I thought, since
we have a few minutes,
oh man, my computer just freaked out.
Oh, yeah.
You got a picture for me, Pachi?
I keep wanting to call you Seiji
because your name ends in I.
[Pachi] Is it the turtle?
[GMR] Yeah.
I heard Tim likes turtles,
so I got a turtle picture.
I love this picture.
This is an ancient belief in India
that the whole universe
is held up by a turtle,
that the universe exists
on the back of a turtle.
Now listen, if you're
wrong about the turtle
that holds up the world,
you're wrong about everything
in the world.
Got it?
If you think the world is being
held up on a turtle's back.
- What's being held up on a turtle's back?
- The world.
- How much stuff is in the world?
- Everything in the world.
- Okay, then you're wrong
about every god damn thing
in the world. Okay, got it?
If you think that world exists
on the back of a turtle,
then how many things are you wrong about?
[laughing]
- Everything on the back.
- How much is that?
- That's everything.
By the way, people are
always bringing me books
all the time.
You don't know.
And I don't know why
especially when I leave a city
or a country, they always give
me some book at the airport.
It's like, "Oh, Gheshe-la, read this,
it's just like what you teach."
I'm like, I don't think so.
But I'm always polite. I take the book.
And I have a game I play with myself
while I'm waiting at the passport line.
I open the book at one
sentence and I look at it,
and if it's not ridiculous,
I might read another page.
But if the one sentence is ridiculous,
then when I get through
Customs, and I make sure
that people aren't looking at me anymore,
and then I throw it out.
I throw the book out and
then my friends are like,
"Geshe-la, why don't you
give it to the charity store
when you get home?"
No, I don't want to
because it's totally wrong.
I don't want to be responsible
for someone else getting a
stupid idea in their mind
that's going to cause them suffering
for the rest of the life.
No, the only thing I can do
with this book is toss it
and hope that the garbage
guy doesn't read it.
I'm not being sectarian. I'm just saying,
if Nagarjuna is correct so
far, then everything we know,
everything that was taught
to me at Princeton University
was wrong.
Everything.
It was all on the back of a turtle.
The basic premise was wrong.
Everything about it was wrong.
One thing can cause another.
That's wrong.
Okay, then all science, all
philosophy, all music, all art,
everything is wrong.
All right, got it?
Everything.
If you think that the world
is on the back of a turtle,
then everything you think
about the world is wrong
on a basic level, on a basic level.
All right.
So don't give me a book unless
it agrees with Nagarjuna
because I'm not interested.
All right. And don't say
it's just like what I teach
because it's not just
like what I'm teaching.
It really frustrates me.
All right. We're going to
do a little Sanskrit lesson.
Don't think this is useless.
When you become a Buddha,
you speak Sanskrit.
So come on, learn a few words now.
It'll get your mind ready for later.
So apekṣya (apekshya).
Say apekshya.
[Students] Apekshya. [GMR] Apekshya, yeah.
Now, this is an
interesting word because...
Christina, when a Sanskrit
word starts with A, it's
a negative.
But here it's not.
And it's very confusing.
So it's not a-pekshya,
it's apa-iksha.
[Christina] Yeah.
[GMR] Yeah, okay, got it?
So yeah.
So it's not a-pekshya, like
a-vidya, ignorance, not knowing.
It's not a-pekshya, it's apa-iksha.
So don't get confused, all right?
- What's that mean in Tibetan?
- It's LTOS PA.
- What LTOS PA mean?
- Depend on the wall.
The ladder depends on the wall.
The fire depends on the wood
and the wood depends on the fire.
Dependent origination.
They both depend on your seeds.
It's not that the fire's
depending on the wood
and it's not that the
woods depend on the fire,
they are both depending on
your brain and your seeds.
Got it?
So dependence becomes crucial.
The word apekshya becomes crucial.
Now, it's so beautiful.
Apa- means away, and away comes from apa-.
Iksha means you had pariksha.
[Student] To see.
[GMR] To see, nice.
So you're looking to
someone else for help.
Hey, Christina, I need
some fingernail clippers.
And I look away from myself to you.
It's called looking away from
yourself to another person
because you need something.
I'm depending on Christina
for the fingernail clippers,
just a few minutes ago.
So that's called apa-iksha,
looking over there for help,
looking for what you need. Hey, Jigme,
can you give me a pizza?
I'm depending on you.
Apekshya, apekshya.
I'm looking away to you.
Got it?
Okay, we had iksha already
when we did pariksha.
Yeah, and then investigate,
looking into something.
Looking around, digging around.
Yeah, and don't forget... By the way, Tim,
you may be interested.
The only one...
This is the Tibetan word is LTOS PA.
L-T-O-S, la-ta-tak-ta-naro-to-sa, LTOS
What's the root of that? For $50.
Wait, you're looking here.
LTA BA which means to look.
So the root of the
Tibetan word is the same
as the root of the Sanskrit word.
When you say dependent
origination in Tibetan,
you're saying look to somebody else.
Got it?
The same root LT.
la-ta-tak-ta
Okay, cool.
All right, that's your Sanskrit lesson.
I'm sorry, that's a tough chapter.
That's maybe the toughest class
we're going to have, maybe.
So don't get discouraged.
Look at it again and again and again.
I spent, I don't know, almost 30 years
trying to figure this stuff out.
So don't get frustrated.
Just keep coming back.
Each time you come back,
you'll understand a little more.
I say,
you can't really do mantras
if you don't understand this stuff.
You can, I mean, obviously
anybody can do mantras,
but if you want them to be powerful,
you have to understand this stuff.
All right, see you guys later.